JOSEPH McDonald, Ph.D.

jpmcd@mit.edu · github.com/jpmcd Brooklyn, NY

Math Ph.D. with 5 years machine learning research and engineering experience in startups and academia. Seeking scientist-engineering role focused on ML/NLP solutions at AI-centered late-stage startup or established tech company. Open to in-person/remote/hybrid roles.

Positions

10/2020 – present

Researcher, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Lincoln Laboratory Supercomputing Center

- · Execute research in machine learning, natural language processing and high performance computing. Publish findings in artificial intelligence conferences.
- · Leader of system-level research of hardware optimizations for datacenter approaches to sustainable machine learning and computing. Findings show significant reductions in energy consumption and carbon impact through modified compute approaches. Projected 7-figure energy savings impact for Laboratory datacenter. NAACL Findings publication on results for NLP application.
 - Media coverage: MIT News [news.mit.edu/2022/taking-magnifying-glas s-data-center-operations-0824], Unite.AI blogpost [www.unite.ai/curbing-the-growing-power-needs-of-machine-learning]
- · Computer vision, AI applications for tornado detection and prediction. Joint work with meteorological division staff. Primary author of publication on approaches for hail detection and hydrometeor classification.
- · Co-wrote successful \$50K Dept. of Defense 2021 SBIR award proposal with RedShred LLC, for developing AI-integrated document processing applications.

1/2020 - 6/2020

AI Technology Consultant, Co-Star, Series A Social Media Startup

- · Developed and advised on machine learning applications for popular social media iOS/Android app.
- · Automated and scaled NLP tasks and toolsets to aid writing staff in creating and editing content.

6/2017 - 4/2019

Machine Learning Scientist, HIFI, Music Tech Startup

- · Research and development optimizing music recommendation engine using Deep Learning/NLP with Spotify and Amazon user data.
- · Wrote engine for mobile app providing swipe-able song recommendations. Developed novel reinforcement learning methods for online learning through app. Designed and trained neural nets for audio analysis.
- · Lead development of analytics platform for new business model using inference-based predictions.

6/2015 - 8/2015

Software Engineering Intern, Nest Labs, Google Inc.

· Internship on Machine Learning Algorithms Team. Developed machine perception algorithms and integrated new Google learning architectures for Nest Cam.

EDUCATION

2019 Ph.D., Mathematics, Courant Institute, New York University
Optimization, Machine Learning, Mathematical Theory for Signal Processing.
2010 B.S., Mathematics, Physics, summa cum laude, Washington and Lee University

SELECT PUBLICATIONS

- · J. McDonald, B. Li, N. Frey, D. Tiwari, V. Gadepally, S. Samsi. Great Power, Great Responsibility: Recommendations for Reducing Energy for Training Language Models. *Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics NAACL*, 2022.
- · J. McDonald, J. Kurdzo, P. Stepanian, M. Veillette, S. Samsi. Performance Estimation for Efficient Image Segmentation Training of Weather Radar Algorithms. 2022 IEEE High Performance Extreme Computing Conference, 2022.
- · N. C. Frey, S. Samsi, J. McDonald, L. Li, C. W. Coley, V. Gadepally. Scalable Geometric Deep Learning on Molecular Graphs. *NeurIPS 2021 AI for Science Workshop*, 2021.
- · J. McDonald, S. Samsi, D. Edelman, C. Byun, J. Kepner, V. Gadepally. Improved Compression for Word Embeddings by Scaling Principal Components. 2021 IEEE High Performance Extreme Computing Conference, 2021.
- · J. McDonald, B. Bernstein, C. Fernandez-Granda. A Sampling Theorem for Deconvolution in Two Dimensions. SIAM Journal on Imaging Sciences, 13(4), 2020.
- · P.S. Bourdon, E. Gerjuoy, J.P. McDonald, and H.T. Williams. Deterministic Dense Coding and Entanglement Entropy. *Physical Review* A, 77, 022305.

Honors and Awards

- · Henry M. MacCracken Doctoral Fellowship, NYU
- · Barry Goldwater Scholar, National Scholarship for STEM
- \cdot George Washington Scholarship, WLU
- · Robinson Award in Mathematics and Science, WLU
- \cdot James McDowell Scholarship, WLU
- · Phi Beta Kappa

SKILLS

- · Python, BASH, Unix, Git
- · PyTorch, TensorFlow, Keras